Hello and welcome back to my video on
writing ionic formulas. And this time
it's going to be part two and we're
going to be looking at how to write
polyatomic ions, which can be actually a
really scary subject for a lot of
introductory students. Um, so we're
going to be following the same steps as
last time with the first video. So we're
still going to be writing our
predictable charges. We're going to be
writing the symbols side by side and
we're still going to be using our swap
drop method. So I saw the periodic table
here. So in case we need it, we have it
available. But what polyatomic ions are,
so it's a very set chart of a of ions
that are all bound together. So we have
all these individual elements that are
most of them are bound to oxygens. So
what these are referred to in this case
is called oxyan ions. So with oxyan
ions, we're always going to have some
sort of non-metal that I'm just going to
label X for now, such as maybe like
carbon, sulfur, nitrogen, uh that are
bound to a set of oxygens. Now this
number of oxygens or N here always has a
set charge for that polyatomic. So for
example, one could be where I have like
CO3 2 minus. So with this one, we have a
carbon bound to three oxygens and it's
always going to have a 2 minus charge to
it. So in this case, this one is known
as this one's carbon, right? And the
ending for this in terms of naming is 8.
So we'll have carbonate would be the
ending. So like another type of
polyatomic gives us typically it's
editing the number of oxygens in the
charge. So or sorry in the actual
element. So if I kind of go one less and
I say all right the charge is going to
stay the same and we have CO2 2 minus
then in this case it would be carbonite
in this situation right so carbonate
carbonate just showing that oxygen
subtraction so there is a table that I
put together for this so for polyatomic
ions the big thing about it is it's all
about how we go through naming them and
trying to understand them but with this
we're just going to focus on balancing
and writing chemical formulas us more
than anything else. So with this
individual chart, we're going to be
mainly focusing on more like carbonates,
uh like things like the eights and I
endings and then a little bit of the
different polyatomics here as well. So
we're going to focus on balancing.
There'll be another video in the future
on naming, but we're going to focus on
formulas for this video. So let's get to
it. So some different things. So with
these, we follow the same rules. We're
going to write our metal first. So,
let's say if I have two different
species, we'll have sodium and then
we'll have uh we'll have um chlorate as
our two species. So, how do we go about
trying to show how these things are
going to be bonding together? So, first
thing is sodium. What is the predictable
charge? We'll go to our periodic table.
So, with this, we can see all right,
sodium is right in that first column
here. So, that's going to be a plus one
charge. Now, for chlorate, we have to go
to our polyatomic sheet. And what we can
see is, all right, well, chlorate is
right around here that I'm highlighting
in a light purple. We'll uh we'll we'll
circle that as well. So, we see it's Cl3
minus1. So, let's write those down. So,
we have Na+
and Cl3 minus. So, how does this work in
terms of balancing charges and swap
drop? Well, the way that we have to
imagine it is that the entire polyatomic
is one single unit. So, it's one unit
for the polyatomic. Okay? So, meaning
that it's almost as if this entire thing
is in parentheses and it the whole
molecule has a negative one charge as a
result. So when we swap drop this what
we're doing is the positive one where
the one in this case it's going to go
outside the parenthesis and the negative
one is going to go still in the same
spot as normal. So when we write this
how is that going to be? Well being that
they're both one that charge is going to
get dropped. So it's going to just be
same as always as sodium chlorate would
be the name for this molecule. Okay, so
sodium chlorate. And like I said, we'll
go over naming in the future, but we're
just dropping those charges. Let's do
one where the charges are not quite so
equal, though. So, let's say if I have
the following where I have a cobalt 3+,
and we'll also bound that with um we'll
do bulfite. So with this one we have
bisulfite
that's HS3 with a -1 charge. So how does
that work entirely when it comes to the
different prefixes? Let's talk about it
for a second. So sulfite
is a 2 minus charge. So we can see that
uh right here right we have sulfite s3 2
minus. So whenever there's a hydrogen in
front of it or it might have the prefix
by in front of it, it edits the charge
by one. So you can see that the charge
is only negative one and there's a
little hydrogen that is sitting in front
of that when it gets altered. So every
time we add a hydrogen, you can see that
the charges go from 2 minus to 1 minus
by adding a hydrogen. So let's go back.
So we have that H.
So 3 minus
now how are we going to swap the
charges? Well like I mentioned last time
this is one entire unit. So when we drop
that the 3+ or that three is going to
the numerical value three is going to
come outside of the parenthesis and then
the the one from the minus is going to
go to the cobalt. So when we write that
cobalt will be cobalt 1, we'll have our
parentheses,
which is just HS3.
And being that cobalt had a three in
front of it, we're going to put that
next to outside of those parentheses. So
it's going to be cobalt 1 HSO3
essentially. So when we name that, this
would be cobalt
3 bulfite.
Now what does that look like on a
elemental picture? Well, it's kind of
the same thing. So being that we have
one cobalt, it's as if we draw just one
CO3 plus and let's just put that in a
it's a little atom and then we have
around it a bunch of HSO3 molecules
all bound around it. So, we have these
little polyatomic ions all bound around.
And being that there's three of them,
we're going to be drawing three
individual polyatomics on each side. So,
that's what it looks like on the
molecular
atomic picture right here. So, this is
our molecular picture where we have
those individual polyatomics and that's
what those parentheses are representing
when you put that three outside of it.
So, let's try a different one. So if we
do um let's say we'll pick calcium
and phosphate. So we'll have phosphate
which is P4 and we can try to find that
on our sheet here. So it's P4 3 minus.
So that would be the charge for that
one. So we'll go back. We'll write that
charge down. So let's swap drop it. So
we're going to bring both those numbers
down. We're going to write our
parentheses around P4. The number is
going to come down. We'll swap drop it.
So what is that going to make? Well, the
calcium
had the three value come towards it. And
now the phosphate
will have two come next to it. So we'll
write that as R2.
So what does that picture kind of look
like? Well, it's almost like we have
three calciums bound together. So if we
kind of try drawing that, let's just put
like alternating. We'll have calciums
here and here. Sort of like this. We'll
draw them in their little elemental
orbs.
And then being that we have for every
three calciums, we have two phosphates.
So we'll put like maybe in the middle
here like one phosphate.
Excuse my handwriting there. I'm drawing
it sideways. And then we'll have another
phosphate like maybe over here like just
showing that it's that 3:2 ratio is
really the important part here. So
that's kind of that's a little bit of
the basics of it. So let's try like a
let's try like a different one here.
Maybe one from like a famous painting or
something like that just to kind of make
it fun. So if we do let's say if you
ever looked at the painting. So a lot of
polyatomics exists in a lot of um
different foods that we eat. Maybe a lot
of the medical industry uses them a lot.
So like foods you see them in like chips
for example like sodium acetate is a
common uh preservative/ like flavoring
agent that you that you will see in
chips or maybe for casting for casts in
the medical industry. Polyatomics are
really common in those. Um so this one I
have the picture for Star Knight from
Vincan Go. Um and it's one of the most
beautiful paintings made and this one
actually has a polyatomic in it. So this
has iron 3 cyanide in it. So what is
that exact structure? So if we kind of
look at this well that three for iron
tells you that all right well we have
iron 3+. Now what is cyanide though? So
why don't we go to our chart and what
we're going to see is that if we look at
our miscellaneous ones here
that cyanide is CN minus. So we're going
to use that one and go through this
particular example. So we'll have iron
and CN minus. So when this is going
through this, we're going to do our swap
drop. We're going to put parentheses
around CN. The number is going to come
next to it. So if we rewrite that,
that's going to be CN in parenthesis
with a three. And then the one from
cyanide will come over to iron and it'll
be FE CN3.
So, and this is the color for Prussian
blue. So, this is one of the what really
gives it that that that blue color that
we see here in the star night painting.
So, I hope this video helped a little
bit and how to use polyatomics and how
to make sure you are balancing them
correctly when you're writing your ionic
formulas. I hope you have a wonderful
day and come back next time for future
videos. Thank you so much.